Guide to the Spy Hop Productions independent film collection 2000-2009
Multimedia Archives, J. Willard Marriott Library, University of Utah
Spy Hop Productions independent film collection
2000-2009
University of Utah Libraries, Special Collections Audio Visual Archives Special Collections 295 South 1500 East Salt Lake City, Utah 84112-0860 (801) 581-8864
A0797
Spy Hop Productions
1 DVD, 1 compact disc and 109 Mini-DV videocassettes.
The Spy Hop Productions independent film collection (2000-2009) consists of raw footage and finished films assembled by elementary and high school aged filmmakers under the tutelage of Spy Hop Productions, a Salt Lake City not-for-profit youth media center specializing in educational solutions through the multimedia arts. This collection is part of the Utah Independent Film Archive (UIFA).
Organizational History
Spy Hop Productions is a not-for-profit youth media center specializing in educational solutions through the multimedia arts. Their mission is to cultivate the visions and voices of an emerging generation - via the big screen, the airwaves, and the world-wide-web. Founded in 1999 by Utah natives Rick Wray and Erik Dodd, Spy Hop Productions was created with a vision to empower underserved youth through multimedia arts education and to meet the demands of the community for after-school programming that helps prepare young people for the digital future. With their experience and expertise in education, multimedia production and business management, Mr. Wray and Mr. Dodd successfully developed the organization from a two-person operation to one that now serves over 600 young people a year and employs over 25 full and part-time employees.
In collaboration with community partners such as the Mayor's Office Youth City Program, the Sundance Institute, the University of Utah Youth Education, the Boys and Girls Club, ArtStart Rowland Hall St. Marks, Art Kids, and the Kennedy Center Imagination Celebration of Salt Lake City, Spy Hop Productions provides a creative and dynamic studio environment where young people of all backgrounds actively engage in the production of their own narratives and solutions to the challenges they face. The young participants involved in Spy Hop's programs have worked with mentors and instructors in multiple media arts disciplines including documentary arts, film and video production, radio, web design, 3D graphics, and animation. In 2004, the young producers' creative works reached local and national audiences exceeding two million people.
The Spy Hop Productions independent film collection (2000-2009) consists of raw footage and finished films assembled by elementary and high school aged filmmakers under the tutelage of Spy Hop Productions, a Salt Lake City not-for-profit youth media center specializing in educational solutions through the multimedia arts. The collection contains narrative, claymation and documentary films and includes extensive footage about Salt Lake City hosting the 2002 Olympic Winter Games. Many films appear on more than one videocassette. This collection is part of the Utah Independent Film Archive (UIFA).
The majority of the materials are arranged chronologically and by subject matter. Completed movies made by Spy Hop filmmakers and students 2000-2003 are followed by raw footage used in documentaries about the 2002 Winter Olympics, Salt Lake City refugees and Salt Lake City's West Side. Compilation discs of the best films and audio tracks from 1999-2009 are found at the end of the inventory.
Materials must be used on-site; no use of original material, access copies will be made available for viewing. Five business days advanced notice required. Access to parts of this collection may be restricted under provisions of state or federal law, condition of the material, or by donor.
1 CD containing records listing the date, title, filmmaker and synopsis of various films undertaken by the company 1996-2003 was transferred to the Manuscripts Division of Speical Collections.
Olympic Winter Games (19th: 2002: Salt Lake City, Utah); Independent filmmakers; Artists--Utah; Fine Arts; Moving Images; Moving images
- "433 Miles" and "The Hour Glass Project", 2000; Mini-DV videocassette (Cassette 1)
  - "433 Miles", 2000 (Video 1)
    A short independent film about five teenagers who decide to take a road trip to Las Vegas to see Wayne Newton in concert. Along the way, they run out of money and find interesting means of procuring funds to continue the journey such as giving cyclists pedicures, dancing for pocket change, and competing in an X-treme Croquet tournament.
  - "The Hour Glass Project", 2000 (Video 2)
    Teens ask other teens about their predictions, preparations and fears about Y2K in an interview on-the-street style documentary.
- Spy Hop shorts, 2000-2002; Mini-DV videocassette (Cassette 2)
  - "Let Them Eat Cake" - narrative, 2000 (Video 1)
    A young boy celebrates his birthday alone with his "Cookie Monster" birthday cake. Montage of the boy and the cake going to the park, playing on the swings and slide, and playing catch until the cake is damaged and the boy must perform "surgery" with icing to repair his playmate. The cake holds a grudge against the boy until he introduces it to a "sexy" female cake and then the boy is alone again as romance blossoms. Boy suffers an anxiety attack and decides to exact revenge by eating the new "girlfriend" cake. The "Cookie Monster" cake catches him in the act and attacks at which point the boy awakens from a dream to find himself sitting at the table of the opening party scene. When he opens the room's door, he is presented with a "Cookie Monster" cake and shuts the door on it.
  - "Released" - narrative, 2000 (Video 2)
    A teenage girl is stuck going on an astrology field trip during the first week of summer when she'd rather be going to see the Ramones in concert. On the journey one of her fellow classmates, Peter, carries with him a small lunch cooler which contains a mysterious secret he guards. In the cooler is some form of insect he nurtures but when he leaves the cooler in the care of the girl, Josh (a trouble-making jock) slips a large beetle into it. Later in the van as they travel to their next stop, Peter opens the cooler to see the beetle. Josh confesses to having taken the butterfly which was apparently in the cooler and accidentally lets the insect fly out the window to be killed on the windshield of a car. On the way home, they open the windows in the van and several butterflies fly into the van and they stop the vehicle to witness a butterfly migration and Peter smiles for the first time during the film.
  - "Sticks and Stones" - narrative, 2000 (Video 3)
    A girl, Beth, and her boyfriend, Cam, help her new roommate move in and have a celebratory dinner. Cam walks in on the new roommate, Amy, and her lesbian girlfriend kissing and is disturbed by it and the fact that his girlfriend lives with a lesbian. When he tells a friend about it, the friend councils him to get to know Amy as he might discover she's cool and they have common interests...other than girls. When he goes over to Beth and Amy's house he meets Gavin, a friend of Amy's, and they talk about Jeeps for a while. In another room Amy tells Beth she hopes Gavin meets someone nice as the breakup with his last boyfriend was difficult. Later Amy's girlfriend confronts Cam about how he avoids Amy and is giving her the cold shoulder because she is a lesbian. After the confrontation, Cam vandalizes Amy's car as Beth spies him in the act from a window. Cam's hatred escalates until he beats Amy with a tire iron.
  - "UP;RIGHT" - documentary, 2000 (Video 4)
    A documentary about Human Rights (particularly dealing with freedom of speech, gay rights, civil rights in relation to race, and freedom of religion) in 2000 through the eyes of Salt Lake teens from diverse backgrounds as they compare and contrast how their lives have benefited from the sacrifices of others in previous generations to procure those rights.
  - ""Run Sheep Run" - claymation, 2000 (Video 5)
    A farmer chases after two of his sheep in order to shear them.
  - "Beach Thief" - claymation, 2000 (Video 6)
    A surfer naps on the beach when a girl tries to steal his surfboard. In the pursuit of the thief and his surfboard, the girl's bathing suit is snagged by a fisherman and the fisherman is pulled into the water where he is then attacked by sharks. The surfer gets his board back.
  - "The Trouble With Music" - claymation, 2000 (Video 7)
    A man sits in a chair when a package is delivered to his door. In the package is a stereo and whatever genre of music the man plays, a person stereotyping the image associated with that type of music appears until he smashes the stereo out of frustration.
  - "Big Nick's Day at the Beach" - claymation, 2001 (Video 8)
    A guy in a thong Speedo finds love at the beach in the form of an elephant. Flash forward five years and a myriad of cross-species, half-elephant/half-men are the product of the love match. This film was produced by students in Rowland Hall St. Mark's School's ArtStart program.
  - "The Princess and the Pokemon" - Bennion Elementary claymation, 2001 (Video 9)
    A princess goes around collecting Pokemon then uses them in a match which Pikachu wins.
  - "The Rolling Head" - Bennion Elementary claymationn, 2001 (Video 10)
    A head rolls around until it sprouts a body.
  - "Godzilla v. King Kong" - Bennion Elementary claymation, 2001 (Video 11)
    Godzilla and King Kong fight it out and Godzilla wins.
  - "A Dog" - Bennion Elementary claymation, 2001 (Video 12)
    A dog wanders around outside sniffing at items and wagging his tail.
  - "A Rumble in the Jungle" - Bennion Elementary claymation, 2001 (Video 13)
    Impressionist-style animals interact with one another.
  - "The Big Concert" - Bennion Elementary claymation, 2001 (Video 14)
    A performer is booed off stage at a concert.
  - "Another Dog" - Bennion Elementary claymation, 2001 (Video 15)
    A dog outside sniffs at some flowers before devouring one of them.
  - "Snail Trail" - Bennion Elementary claymation, 2001 (Video 16)
    A snail leaves a trail of slime behind it and other insects run into the mess.
  - "Crazy Clouds" - Bennion Elementary claymation, 2001 (Video 17)
    A young girl asks the clouds to go away and let the sun come out.
  - "Space Cats" - claymation, 2002 (Video 18)
    A group of flying cats search outer space for treasure but just when they are about to take hold of the treasure evil dogs capture them. A rocket ship-flying turtle comes to the cats' rescue and as a reward, is granted half of the treasure.
  - "The Meadowlark Massacre" - claymation, 2002 (Video 19)
    A playground bully gets his just desserts when he messes with two children who run into a haunted house to avoid him.
  - "The Ends of the Earth" - claymation, 2002 (Video 20)
    A school bus full of animals and a blind man drive around town until the driver, a worm, is abducted by a bird and the blind man takes the wheel accidentally driving them all off of a cliff and into the center of the earth. When they finally surface, they find themselves under the sea and so return to the core to find a better point of exit. When they resurface again, the worm returns to the bus after having escaped the bird.
  - "Sour Apples" - claymation, 2002 (Video 21)
    A lizard attempts to get an apple off of a tree but fails. When it gives up and leaves, the apple falls to the ground. Two lizards duel and one bites the other's head off.
  - "Dog Gone Bone" - claymation, 2002 (Video 22)
    A dog buries his bone before going to sleep. The next morning he awakes and attempts to dig up the bone but digs up several other items by mistake such as a key and a remote control, until he finally finds his bone.
  - "Microcosmos" - claymation, 2002 (Video 23)
    A large black amoeba attempts to eat a particle only to have it stolen by a small red amoeba. The black amoeba then eats the red amoeba but is attacked by its companions who break the large black amoeba into smaller ones. The group of black amoebas then meets the red amoebas in battle when a zoom out shot show all of this is taking place in a glass of water being drunk by a man.
  - "Alien Vacation" - claymation, 2002 (Video 24)
    An alien dog lands on Earth. After eating several vehicles and growing very large he is picked back up by his spaceship and leaves.
  - "Guinea Pig Mania!!!" - claymation, 2002 (Video 25)
    A scientist develops a superhuman formula and decides to test it on his guinea pig. Thinking his experiment failed, the scientist donates the animal to the local pet shop. The animal has been altered however and is dangerous and causes a great deal of destruction to the pet shop who then sells it to NASA for the Animals in Space Program. After being launched into space, the guinea pig is hurtled into space where the sun's radiation "undoes" all of the harmful effects of the experiment and the animal returns to the pet shop where it is welcomed back to live there forever.
  - "Home Under the Range" - claymation, 2002 (Video 26)
    City mice move to the desert where they encounter the locals. When the city mice realize their television antenna didn't survive the move, the son of the city mice and the daughter of the desert mice work out a solution to unite their families by connecting their burrows and sharing a TV.
- Spy Hop shorts 2000, Sundance documentary workshop 2002, 1999-2002; Mini-DV videocassette (Cassette 3)
  - "Jules" - narrative, 2000 (Video 1)
    The first true Spy Hop Production, "Jules," is the story of a young man suffering from a neurological disorder impairing his ability to correctly identify fruit flavors, struggles with his disorder and its affects on his social life in this mockumentary-styled French language narrative short film.
  - "Baby Roller Sports" - narrative, 2000 (Video 2)
    A window-shopping mother is distracted as her baby's stroller rolls down the hill, hits a rock and sends baby (a doll) flying onto the open tailgate of a truck and off on a road trip. A Good Samaritan finds the stroller and attempts to return it to the owner when the truck passes by and hits a bump sending the baby flying through the air once again and into the stroller. The momentum returns the stroller to the side of the mom who didn't even notice the baby was missing.
  - HBO interview, 2000 (Video 3)
    "Jules" director and actors interviewed by HBO's 30x30 Kids Films about the making of the film and how they converted Ogden and Salt Lake City into France for the film.
  - "Mail Order Granny" - narrative, 2000 (Video 4)
    Two kids see a late night commercial and decide to call the 1-800 number to order a mail-order granny of their own. After assembling the Granny, the kids put her to work cleaning and baking cookies for them until she short-circuits and comes after them attacking all who cross her path. The delivery man rescues them with a recall notice and takes out Granny's batteries.
  - "Rocky Bilbordo: A Story of Triumph" - narrative, 2000 (Video 5)
    A champion thumb wrestler is offered a bribe to throw his upcoming match. After allowing the competitor to win, Rocky is ashamed and begins training for a rematch. After seeing the competitor at a cafe one day, Rocky assaults the man and cuts off his thumb to gain back his thumb wrestling "belt."
  - "Peter Pam vs. Captain Cook" - narrative, 1999 (Video 6)
    A nefarious cook holds the maitra d and two patrons of his restaurant hostage after his cooking is criticized for being too sticky. Peter Pam comes to the rescue with a can of cooking spray to release the hostages to save the day.
  - "When I Grow Up: The Real Deal" - Sundance documentary workshop, 2002 (Video 7)
    Three children are asked what they would like to do when they grow up and why, then a person in that profession talks about their job and why they chose to go into that field (i.e. fireman, teacher, policeman, etc.).
  - "The Good Stuff" - Sundance documentary workshop, 2002 (Video 8)
    The manager of a Clean Flicks location is interviewed about the store's business involving the post-release editing of motion pictures for content such as offensive language and sexual or graphically violent content. In contrast, the director of the Sundance Film Festival gives his views on the matter.
  - "My Life: Goran Rogonjic" - Sundance documentary workshop, 2002 (Video 9)
    A Bosnian refugee tells his story about why he and his family left their home and immigrated to the US as well as how life has changed for them since coming to Salt Lake to reside.
  - "Love's Beginnings" - Sundance documentary workshop, 2002 (Video 10)
    A seventeen-year-old, Brittany, talks about teen pregnancy. Her mother discusses the difficulties of having a daughter who is an unwed teenage mother when she was a wed teenage mother, while Brittany's grandmother talks about the loss of her teenage years because of her decision to marry and become a mother by the time she was eighteen and her regrets about not having dated more people before marrying.
  - "Peer Pressure" - Sundance documentary workshop, 2002 (Video 11)
    A teen discusses his ideas on the positive and negative uses for peer pressure, then interviews two fellow teens, Spencer & Jenna, who have used peer pressure positively and John, who was influenced by peer pressure to try illegal drugs which put him in the hospital and nearly killed him.
  - "A Pagan in Zion" - Sundance documentary workshop, 2002 (Video 12)
    A white witch in Utah talks about her beliefs and how those beliefs affect her daily life, her family, and her interaction with her neighbors and the community.
  - "Walk-In Closet" - Sundance documentary workshop, 2002 (Video 13)
    Four men share their "coming out" stories, give advise to others who fear admitting they are homosexual, and talk about how their sexuality affects their lives and their inter action with friends, family and the community.
  - "The Order of the Star-Spangled Student" - Sundance documentary workshop, 2002 (Video 14)
    Six students on the street are asked a question about World War II, of which only two answer correctly. Concerned with the lack of knowledge US children have about their country's history; this film discusses the connection between September 11th attacks and the lack of knowledge of US history by the nation's population.
  - "Climbing: A Personal Revelation" - Sundance documentary workshop, 2002 (Video 15)
    A young writer/filmmaker parallels perseverance in the pursuit of goals to climbing as she interviews a professional rock climber who gives his own views about goals, overcoming fears and reservation, and the elation of success that drives him toward the next obstacle in any aspect of his life.
- "Anima", "...IST" and "Frame", 2002-2003; Mini-DV videocassette (Cassette 4)
  - "Anima", 2002 (Video 1)
    A janitor at an art museum meets a mysterious young woman one night that comes to visit him every night during his shift. She questions him about his former dreams to be a sculptor and encourages him to pick it back up. In the end, the janitor realizes she was merely a figment of his imagination.
  - "...IST", 2003 (Video 2)
    A teen girl searches for herself and starts investigating feminism. After founding a club on extreme feminist principles, she has a nervous breakdown and moves on to environmentalism.
  - "Frame", 2003 (Video 3)
    A photojournalist, who worked on the front during the Vietnam War, is confronted years later by a colleague at the institution where he has been for twenty years after the war struggling with the guilt which has consumed him for his inaction during the events which scared him for life. The two men help to heal one another by sharing their experiences, discussing their flashbacks and nightmares, and discussing photography as a therapeutic means to recovery.
- Spy Hop shorts, 2002; Mini-DV videocassette (Cassette 5)
  - "Watch What You're Watching" - narrative, 2002 (Video 1)
    Two young men are engrossed in a reality police television show when the police enter their home and carry one of the young men's father's away. Unaware that what they are watching on television is happening behind them, one of the men comments "That guy looked like your dad," while the other marvels at the television "It did look like my dad."
  - "The Raft" - narrative, 2002 (Video 2)
    A boy listens as his grandfather with short-term memory loss recounts (again) the story of how he blew up a raft of Japanese sailors during World War II when in command of a US ship turning the regularly heard story into a confession of guilt harbored for nearly 60 years.
  - "Microcosmos" - claymation, 2002 (Video 3)
  - "A Pagan in Zion" - documentary, 2002 (Video 4)
  - "Dog Gone Bone" - claymation, 2002 (Video 5)
  - "I Am Spam" - narrative, 2002 (Video 6)
    While watching television, a boy's desire for the canned lunch meat, Spam, is peaked and he goes on a crazed search of his house to find a can of his favorite food. When he discovers he is out of Spam he goes to the local market only to have the last can purchased by another customer a few steps ahead of him. Following the girl who bought the Spam back to her apartment in the same building in which he lives, the boy sneaks into her apartment where he finds the girls has purchased the Spam to feed her dog. Without hesitation the boy then begins eating the Spam out of the dog bowl side-by-side with the animal.
  - "Silver Funk" - experimental, 2002 (Video 7)
    An experimental film showing a series of shots concerning the eyes and eye related procedures such as eye exams, surgery, and putting in contact lenses in Eisensteinian relation to one another.
  - "Messages: 2002 Olympic Diary" - documentary (Video 8)
    Adolescent filmmakers explore the affect the 2002 Olympic Games would have on Salt Lake City as it is perceived by the world, how the city might change to welcome those unfamiliar with its culture and what sort of involvement the Latter-Day Saint Church might have upon the Winter Games. Particular attention is given to conceptions about the state by outsiders due to the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints (LDS Church), liquor laws, and diversity.
  - "Michael Cane Madness" - music video, 2002 (Video 9)
    A music video styled short about a young man who believes he is British actor, Michael Cane. The young man is chased by fans, reads about his idol, and dresses up to impersonate him until his deception is discovered by two young fans causing him to seek psychiatric help.
  - "The Farm" - narrative, 2002 (Video 10)
    Teens from across the US are abducted and sent to an "Indoctrination Camp" where they become subjects in an attempt to conform them to mainstream society as punishment for offenses such as "sleeping at a Brittany Spears concert," "gothic style of dress," or even "protesting WTO." At the camp the abductees are constantly monitored and are forced to listen to a barrage of mantras such as "a fat body is not a fit body," "the color is blue," and "a white smile is a happy smile," while being reprogrammed into consumer-driven drones.
  - "Space Cats" - claymation, 2002 (Video 11)
  - "Will They Ever Go Back?" - documentary, 2002 (Video 12)
    A short documentary exploring what it is to be a refugee in the United States. Young men and women are interviewed about their experiences as refugees from their homelands who seek to create a home in the US.
- Spy Hop shorts, 2002-2003 Spring; Mini-DV videocassette (Cassette 6)
  - "Watch What They're Watching" - public service announcement, 2002 (Video 1)
    A short informative public service announcement styled piece urging adults to monitor the television content viewed by children in their home.
  - "Walk-In Closet" - documentary, 2002 (Video 2)